A Guide to the Wade H. Brown papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA010
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wade H. Brown papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
1911-1942
Rockefeller Archive Center
Brown, Wade H.
FA010
0.88 Cubic Feet 2 document cases
File Plan
Former Classification: I 450 B815
Scope and Contents
Bibliography, biographical material, correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, reprints. Includes material about the development of the drug Tryparsamide for chemotherapy of African sleeping sickness and syphilis. Correspondents include John Auer (1926) and Arthur S. Loevenhart (1914-1926).
Biographical / Historical
Wade Hampton Brown (1878-1942) was a research physician in pathology at The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, 1913-1942. He specialized in the study of the biology of syphilitic infections. His work in experimental chemotherapy of various trypanosomal and spirochetal infections affecting man and certain domestic animals resulted in the arsenical compound tryparsamide for the treatment of African sleeping sickness and in the therapy of general paresis. This was followed by a long series of studies on constitutional factors and physical environment in relation to disease, the inheritance of disease types and various genetic concepts.
Many of his publications were co-authored with Louise Pearce.
Member of: Association of American Physicians American Society of Pathologists and Bacteriologists American Society for Experimental Pathology American Society for Pharm. and Experimental Therapeutics Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine A.A.A.S. Sigma Xi Nu Sigma Nu
Chronology
1878 Born October 18, Sparta, Georgia
1899 B.S., University of Nashville
1902-1903 Graduate student at the University of Chicago
1907 M.D., Johns Hopkins University
1907-1908 Instructor in pathology, University of Virginia
1908-1910 Instructor in pathology, University of Wisconsin
1910-1911 Assistant professor in pathology, University of Wisconsin
1911-1913 Professor in pathology, University of North Carolina
1913-1914 Associate in Pathology and Bacteriology, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research(RIMR), New York, NY
1914-1922 Associate Member, RIMR
1922-1942 Member, RIMR (1935 transferred to Princeton Laboratories)
1942 Died August 4, Rice Lake, Wisconsin
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of The Rockefeller University administration. Received September 1974.
Custodial History
The papers in Box 2 were found with various patent related documents that had been stored in the Welch Hall-Rockefeller University archives vault. Dr. Brown is the principal correspondent, and the papers have been arranged as part of his Institute file.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Related Materials
Official patent correspondence has been arranged with FA137 Rockefeller University records, Business Manager, Subject Files (Series 7)
Arrangement
As received.
Brown, Wade H.
- Biographical material, photographs, memorial minute, bibliography, reports on development of scientific work (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Report of death, telegrams, posthumous letters, committee for completing work on constitution (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Administrative correspondence, 1911-1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes letters on early grants and on joining Institute staff. 1924 correspondence deals with patents and release of tryparsamide.
- Administrative correspondence, 1930-1942 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Correspondence with Simon Flexner and Waldo Flinn dealing largely with breeding problems and costs of rabbit colonies for constitution studies. Includes study of epidemic in rabbit colony and includes details of arrangements made to move Dr. Brown's laboratory to the Department of Animal Pathology at Princeton.
- Collected Reprints, 4 volumes
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1923 January-June (Box 2, Folder 6)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1923 September-December (Box 2, Folder 7)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1924 January-February (Box 2, Folder 8)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1924 March (Box 2, Folder 9)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1924 April-December (Box 2, Folder 10)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Loevenhart, Arthur S. Correspondence, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- re: Tryparsamide work - A.S. Loevenhart Mss. 16 pp. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Popular account of work at the University of Wisconsin (by Ruby Black?)
- re: Tryparsamide work - "Statement as to the agreement entered into with Dr. Loevenhart for the Study of Tryparsamide", ca. 1924 January (Box 2, Folder 14)
- re: Tryparsamide work - re: C. Leake's paper in "Science"., 1925 Seotember 18 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Copies of unused Mss re: Loevenhart statement in "Science". (Box 2, Folder 16)
- re: Tryparsamide work - "Science" issues 1925 18 September and 25 December (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Reprint of W.H. Brown article, 1925 October 16.
- re: Tryparsamide work - Auer, John, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Chicago Medical Society Bulletin 8, 1923 December 15 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- re: Tryparsamide work - Clipping, The Capitol Times (?), Madison, WI, 1926 January 5 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  See radio program schedule on verso.